Guide to the Association of Internes and Medical Students, Harvey Cushing Chapter Records
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
Association of Internes and Medical Students. Harvey Cushing Chapter Records
1946-1949
Ms Coll 19
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
0.5
(1 box)
The Association of Internes and Medical Students (AIMS), which advocated for progressive causes such as national health insurance, was organized by medical school chapters. The Harvey Cushing Chapter was the Yale School of Medicine chapter. The collection contains correspondence, a report, and minutes of the chapter and material on national AIMS activities.
Association of Internes and Medical Students. Harvey Cushing Chapter
Association of Internes and Medical Students
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Found in the collection. Provenance unknown.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
The Association of Internes and Medical Students (AIMS) was founded in 1941 when the Interne Council of America (ICA), formed in 1936, joined with the Association of Medical Students, formed in 1937. AIMS promoted a number of progressive causes such as national health insurance and cooperation with medical students overseas. Because AIMS endorsed what were considered radical ideas in the days of McCarthyism, the organization was suspected of being subversive. Increasing attacks and lack of funds forced it to disband by about 1952. The Student American Medical Association was founded in 1950 to counter AIMS.
Scope and Contents
The Association of Internes and Medical Students (AIMS) was organized by local chapters. The Harvey Cushing Chapter, the Yale School of Medicine chapter, compiled or collected the documents in this collection. The chapter organized lecture series with talks by prominent health professionals and explored such issues as the distribution of medical care, blacks in medicine and medical care of minorities, universal health insurance, and health care in other countries. Documents include correspondence by members of the chapter, especially Lewis P. Rowland (YSM, 1948) and Ruth Leyendecker (YSM, 1951); an annual report and incomplete chapter minutes; documents related to national conventions, and memoranda distributed to the chapter; and issues of the AIMS journal The Interne, 1948. Some of the documents relate to the International Union of Students, the National Society for Medical Research, the National Youth Assembly Against National Military Training, and the American Medical Association. Halsted R. Holman (YSM 1949), president of AIMS, responded to insinuations of communism by the AMA.
Draft -- United States; Interns (Medicine) -- Connecticut; National health insurance -- United States; Medical students -- Connecticut; Student movements; Vivisection; Correspondence; Medical students; The Interne; Cort, Ruth Leyendecker; Holman, Halsted, 1925-; Rowland, Lewis P., 1925-2017; American Medical Association; Association of Internes and Medical Students; International Union of Students; National Society for Medical Research (U.S.); National Youth Assembly Against Universal Military Training; Yale University. School of Medicine
- Correspondence of the Harvey Cushing Chapter, 1946-1949 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Correspondence of Yale School of Medicine student members of the Harvey Cushing Chapter of AIMS, especially Lewis P. Rowland (YSM 1948 ) and Ruth Leyendecker (Cort) (YSM, 1951). Most of the correspondence is with potential invited speakers. They included Yale faculy members such as Ashley Oughterson and C.E.-A. Winslow, as well as such out-of-town physicians as Michael M. Davis, Chairman of the Committee on Research in Medical Economics, and Montague Cobb, Howard University.
- Harvey Cushing Chapter report and minutes, 1946-1949 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Includes the annual report for 1946-1947 with a list of speakers and other chapter activities, and handwritten minutes of later meetings. Also included are mimeographed letters from AIMS asking chapters to discuss national health insurance.
- AIMS Constitution and information on AIMS., ca. 1946-1949 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Includes Constitution, application for membership, "What is AIMS," and "Association of Internes and Medical Students."
- National convention, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Mimeographed "Organization Bulletin" providing a "preliminary report of the resolution adopted at the National Convention held in Philadelphia, December 27, 28, 29, 1946."
- National convention, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  "Proceedings, A.I.M.S. Convention, December, 1947; Issue of A.I.M.S. Pulse, mimeograph newsletter of the National Executive Committee of AIMS, February 1947; and "Student Bill of Rights" adopted by the National Student Association, 1947.
- National convention, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Program of the National Convention, December 28-30, 1948; "Resolutions Passed by AIMS Convention, December 1948"; various mimeograph memoranda from earlier in 1948; and three issues of the A.I.M.S. Pulse.
- AIMS, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Issue of the A.I.M.S. Pulse, February 1949.
- AIMS and the International Union of Students, 1948 and n.d. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  AIMS resolution to reaffirm affiliation with the International Union of Students (IUS), an international organization of medical students, 1948; Report to the AIMS Convention concerning the Medical Faculty Bureau of the International Union of Students; Constitution and various other mimeographed documents concerning the IUS; printed brochure on the IUS; and Program of the Student International Clinical Congress held in England in 1948.
- AIMS and "universal military training", 1947-1948 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Memoranda to AIMS chapters concerning a resolution passed opposing "universal military training" (the draft). Some are by Dr.Walter J. Lear for the Executive Committee of the National Assembly Against Universal Military Training. The folder includes several documents by this organization. Also included is a pamphlet, National Council Against Conscription, An Analysis of the Report of the President's Advisory Committee on Universal Training, July, 1947.
- AIMS and the National Society for Medical Research, 1947-1949 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  The National Society for Medical Research advocated for the use of animals in medical research and counteracted anti-vivisection movements. The Society reached out to members of AIMS. Included is a mimeograph letter from Executive Secretary Ralph Rohweder to Ruth Leyendecker at Yale, and various other publications of the Society.
- AIMS and the American Medical Association, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Mimeographed correspondence consisting of an anonymous letter to the AMA Council on Medical Education suggesting that AIMS provided "an entering wedge and a substantial bloc of communism in American Medicine" and that the International Union of Students was a "communistic organization" supported by the Communist Party; a lengthy rebuttal by Halsted R. Holman (YSM 1949), President of the National Executive Committee of AIMS, to Dr. Morris Fishbein of AMA, April 26, 1948; and a brief letter to Holman from AMA, September 14, 1948.
- The Interne, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  The Interne was the journal of the Association of Internes and Medical Students. The folder contains six issues spanning from June 1948 through December 1948 and mimeograph letters concerning the The Interne.
- Miscellaneous pamphlets (Box 1, Folder 13)
  A Primer of Parliamentary Law; a brochure for the World Student Service Fund; and Films for Democracy.